

About Me



Hi, my name's Jewel Johnson. I completed my Masters in Biological Sciences from the Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Thiruvananthapuram (ISER-TVM). My research interests include behavioural ecology, vised rect of pollution and climate change on pollinating insects, social behaviour and interactions in social insects. I have had experience in doing experiments with the Asian Honeybee (Apis ceana), the Glant Honeybee (Apis dozsate) and the Greater Banded Homet (Vespa tropica). I am also proficient in R programming and have experience in data visualization and data wranging using various packages available in A.

Education

Integrated BS-MS Dual Degree in Biological Sciences

Indian Institute of Science Education and Research
August 2015 - August 2020 earch Thiruvananth

CGPA 8.31/10

Biology with Maths, Class XII

o Indian Higher Secondary S August 2013 - June 2015

St. Michael's Anglo Indian Higher Seco June 2013

Skillset

Research Experience

This project was carried out under the supervision of Prof. Hema Somanathan. The Giant Honeybee (Apis dorsata) is

Major Degree Thesis IISER-TVM, India May 2019 - April 2020

known to be facultative noctural species of bees who occasionally forage on flowers during crepuscular and full-mon known to be facultative noctural species of bees who occasionally forage on flowers during crepuscular and full-mon periods. Despite having day adapted eyes, it is not known how A dorsata can forage at low light conditions. So my project was aimed at understanding the visual ecology A dorsata.

During this project, I developed a nove training paradigm for training A dorsata as they are open nesting species that are quite aggressive and cannot be reared or handled in a controlled lab environment. I performed classical conditioning experiments and conducted video observations. I learned how to use the software SORIS for video analysis. Data analysis and data visualization was done using R.

Semester Project

May 2018 - Dec 2018

For this project, I managed and stored around 100 different species of insect specimens and performed basic morphometric measurements on them using the ImageJ software.

Summer Internship

IISER-TVM, India May 2018 - Dec 2018

It is known that honeybees rely on pollen as their primary source of protein and we also know that flowers primarily pollinated by honeybees contain a cocktail of amino adds in its nectar. In this project I investigated the role of phenylalanine, an essential amino acid for honeybees in terms of learning in the Asian Honeybee (Apic serans). During this project I performed classical conditioning experiments and did data analysis using R.

tive learning and olfactory preferences of the Greater Banded Hornet (Vespa tropica)

Summer Internship

May 2017 - June 2017

The Greater Banded Homet (Vespa tropica) is a hymenopteran predator who is declared as an invasive species by m countries in Europe. They are also generalists who employ a wide variety of foraging strategies which makes the excellent model organisms to study cognition and vision.

In this study, I performed classical conditioning experiments to study colour and shape learning abilities in V. tropica. Later I checked their Offactory preferences by performing a dual choice experiment. The data from the experiments were analyzed using R. I also received first-hand experience in writing the manuscript of this study which was later published in 2021. This mg study also garnered media attention from The Wire Science.

Awards and Honors

- Achieved all India rank of \$2 in Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE) 2020 in Ecology and Evolution Paper, GATE score 606 and GATE Reg no: EY20S57226002.
 Achieved all India rank of \$1 in Council of Scientific & Industrial Research Junior Research Fellowship (CSR-VRF) and National Eligibility Test (NET) Exam 2019 Fellowship (Reg no. 367970). This is the qualifying exam for PhD and lectureship in India.
 Recipient of Innovation in Science Pursuit for Inspired Research (INSPIRE) fellowship. For the duration of 5 years of study in IISER-TVM.

Publications

Balamurali, G. S., Reshnuraj, R. S., <u>Johnson, J.</u> Kodandaramaiah, U., & Somanathan, H. (2021). Visual associative learning and olfactory preferences of the greater banded homet, Vespa tropica. In Insectes Sociaux (Vol. 68, Issues 2-3, pp. 217–226). Springer Science and Business Media LLC: https://doi.org/10.0079/s00409-01.00826.w. (Vol. one mail in eff you want a copy)

Conferences & Presentations

- r preferences in a hymenopteran predator I Biology across kingdoms : School of Biology Symposium and
- router. Visual associative learning and odour preferences in a hymenopleran predator I Biology across kingdoms: School of Biology Symposium and Department day (September 2019) IISER-TVM, India

 Presentation: Role of phenylalanine in learning in Asian honeybee (Apris cerana) I Second Bangalore Meeting On Asian Bees (March 2019) I NCBS Bangalore, India
- India

 Poster Visual associative learning in the Greater Banded Homet (Vespa tropica) I Young Ecologists Talk & Interact (YETI) 2018 (January 2018) I Maharaja
 Sayajirao University of Baroda, India

Extra Curricular Activities

- R programming enthusiast. Made tutorials for ggosts to gram to ggo ackages in R.
 Makes data visualizations at whatshisdata, an initiative to promote science communication for the public.
 Co-founder of The Ecological Society of IISER-TVM, a student body for promoting environmental awareness and safe guarding the greeney in the campus.
 Initiated EcoGOC, an ambitious project for mapping the entire fauna and flora in IISER-TVM via INaturalist.
 Received best exhibit award for the project presentation on DNA Hard drives in the IISER-TVM Annual Science Fest (2016).

Interests and Hobbies

- Birding
 Teaching
 Trekking and cycling
- ıme please click h